"Listen. Listen to what the beetle is saying." I would spend hours and hours listening to the little beetle rolling a huge ball of dung, and while at it, I heard a variety of environmental sounds. With the keenest of ears, I would hear family chatter, laughter, the wind howling and even crickets chirping. All these sounds crisscrossed into each other, and I would hear rhythm in between. Then I would beat my plate with a spoon and my chest with my tiny hands trying to recreate what I was hearing. I have been beating the same plates, shakers, drums, pans and so much more ever since to become a professional drummer and percussionist. (Applause) As I grew up, subconsciously, I felt a strong urge to hide my newfound hobby. Even without it being said out loud, I knew that somehow it was wrong to do what I was doing. In most of the ceremonies, I noticed that most of the women and girls were not in sight, but when they were, I noticed that they would wear their dancing skirts and shake their waists off, singing, clapping, ululating, while the men filled up the rhythm section. A few years later, I came to understand what tradition and culture meant, and what was considered taboo or otherwise. In the majority of African cultures, women have been forbidden to play drums and percussion for a very long time. I believe this taboo stems from the psychological and traditional belief that the woman is an inferior being. I grew up hearing that the place of the woman is in the kitchen or in the other room. Mhm? (Laughter) Women had been brainwashed and led on for so long until we had fallen victim and actually started believing in this ourselves. This, coupled with the lack of interest to educate women, played a major, major role in etching this into our minds. The sounds of the drum provoke emotion and movement. Essentially, the drum is a very sensual instrument. Once at a festival, a man asked me how I dared put a drum in between my legs. I have been considered loose and dirty for playing an instrument. I have repeatedly been questioned why I would choose to play drums instead of practicing journalism, which I studied for my undergraduate, which has been termed "more decent." The sight of a woman playing drums enfeebles her, makes her less feminine, less desirable, but all this optimally puts her on a lower social stand. Drumming has essentially represented the strong African heritage, and its importance can be seen in the many aspects of the African tradition. Many communities encompass drumming in their day-to-day activities, and still do up to date, from childbirths to initiation ceremonies, welcoming ceremonies, marriages and even burials. However, this same drum is disappearing very fast from the music scene, and the traditional genre is losing its popularity very quickly amongst the people. Inspired by the need to preserve this culture, I am teaching the significance and the importance of the drum to young boys, women and girls. In my journey as a percussion teacher, I have realized that very many women actually want to play the drum, but at the same time, they fear it. Some fear how society will perceive them. Others fear the physical pain that comes with playing. Oh yes, it's not that easy. Some, because their spouses don't approve of them, and others generally fear the responsibility of being a bearer of culture. I believe, or I think that all these fears are etched in the collective feminine cautiousness because when we learn of the atrocities that have happened to women, continentally especially, it serves as a constant reminder that one step out of our designated place may end up in very serious consequences.
"Escucha. Escucha lo que dice el escarabajo". Me pasaba horas y horas escuchando al pequeño escarabajo que hacía rodar una enorme bola de estiércol, y mientras lo observaba oía una variedad de sonidos circundantes. Aguzando al máximo mis oídos, oía las charlas familiares, las risas, el rugido del viento y hasta el canto de los grillos. Todos estos sonidos se entrecruzaban y yo percibía un ritmo entre ellos. Luego golpeaba mi plato con una cuchara y me batía el pecho con las manitas tratando de recrear lo que oía. Desde entonces sigo golpeando los mismos platos, maracas, tambores, ollas y muchas otras cosas para llegar a ser baterista y percusionista profesional (Aplausos) A medida que iba creciendo, sentía inconscientemente la imperiosa necesidad de ocultar mi nuevo pasatiempo. Y aunque no lo decía en voz alta, sabía que eso no estaba nada bien. En la mayoría de las ceremonias, notaba que casi todas las mujeres y las niñas no se mostraban pero, cuando lo hacían, aparecían con sus faldas de baile y movían las caderas, cantando, batiendo palmas, ululando, mientras los hombres se encargaban de la parte rítmica. Años después, logré comprender el significado de la tradición y de la cultura, y de lo que se consideraba tabú o no. En la mayoría de las culturas africanas, las mujeres tienen prohibido tocar los tambores o hacer percusión desde hace mucho tiempo. Creo que este tabú se origina en la creencia psicológica y tradicional de que la mujer es un ser inferior. Crecí escuchando a otros decir que el lugar de la mujer está en la cocina o en la otra habitación. ¿Mm? (Risas) Las mujeres fueron objeto de un lavado de cerebro durante largo tiempo hasta que fuimos víctimas y empezamos a creerlo nosotras mismas. Esto, junto con la falta de interés por educar a la mujer, tuvo una enorme influencia para que quedara grabado en nuestra mente. El sonido de un tambor provoca emoción y movimiento. El tambor es, esencialmente, un instrumento muy sensual. Una vez, en un festival, un hombre me preguntó cómo me atrevía a ponerme un tambor entre las piernas. Me han llegado a tildar de mujer fácil y sucia por tocar un instrumento. Muchas veces me han cuestionado por qué elegí tocar el tambor en lugar de dedicarme al periodismo, que era lo que estudiaba en la universidad, actividad que era vista como "más decente". Una mujer que toca el tambor ¿acaso se ve más débil, menos femenina, menos deseable? En el mejor de los casos, la coloca en un nivel social inferior. La percusión representa esencialmente el gran legado africano y su importancia se refleja en los numerosos aspectos de la tradición africana. Muchas comunidades incluyen la percusión en sus actividades diarias, y lo hacen hasta el día de hoy, desde nacimientos hasta ceremonias de iniciación, ceremonias de bienvenida, casamientos e incluso funerales. Sin embargo, este mismo tambor está desapareciendo muy rápido del escenario musical, y el género tradicional está empezando a perder popularidad muy rápido entre la gente. Inspirada por la necesidad de preservar esta cultura, doy clases sobre el significado y la importancia del tambor a mujeres y niños. En mi experiencia como maestra de percusión, noté que había muchísimas mujeres ansiosas por tocar el tambor pero al mismo tiempo tienen miedo. Algunas temen el juicio social. Otras el dolor físico asociado a la ejecución del instrumento. Les aseguro, no es nada fácil. Otras, porque sus esposos no están de acuerdo, y otras porque temen la responsabilidad de ser representantes de una cultura. Pienso que todos estos miedos están grabados en la cautela colectiva de la mujer porque las atrocidades cometidas contra ella, especialmente en nuestro continente, nos recuerdan permanentemente que si nos apartamos un solo paso del lugar que nos han asignado, podríamos enfrentar serias consecuencias.
Well, I use my drum to tell my story and my people's stories. My roots shaped me and my culture is here to stay with me. Women can be custodians of culture, too. We are born to bring forth life, to nurture it. We can definitely preserve our traditions very, very excellently. My drum and I, we are here to stay. (Applause) We are definitely here to stay. If women have led countries, women have gone to space, women have won Grammys, then the same, same women can play the drum and play it -- to a five-star rating? No, to a million-star rating. Thank you. (Applause) (Chiming) (Metallic drumming) (Rattling) (Drumming) (Applause)
Pues bien, yo uso mi tambor para contar mi historia personal y la historia de mi gente. Mis raíces me han formado y mi cultura estará siempre en mí. Las mujeres también pueden ser guardianas de la cultura. Hemos nacido para crear vida, para alimentarla. No hay dudas de que podemos conservar las tradiciones de la mejor manera. Este tambor y yo, hemos llegado para quedarnos. (Aplausos) Sin duda hemos llegado para quedarnos. Si hay mujeres que han liderado países, que han ido al espacio, que han ganado premios Grammy, entonces las mismas mujeres pueden tocar el tambor y llegar a un nivel de... ¿10 estrellas? No, a un nivel de un millón de estrellas. Gracias. (Aplausos) (Tintineo) (Sonido de platillos de metal) (Sonido de maracas) (Tamborileo) (Aplausos)